Moss Roberts Vietnam War Research Files TAM.403
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Moss Roberts Vietnam War Research Files
1849-1979
1960-1975
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Roberts, Moss, 1937-
TAM.403
5.5 Linear Feet In 11 manuscript boxes
Moss Roberts (1937-) is a Professor of East Asian Studies at New York University where he was first appointed in 1968. As a founding member of the Committee of Concerned Asian Scholars – a group which was founded in 1968 with the purpose of challenging what they saw as assumptions that led to the Vietnam War – Roberts has written articles for their journal, formerly the Bulletin of Concerned Asian Scholars from 1968 to 2000. This collection consists of multiple primary and some secondary sources largely from the communist perspective of the Vietnam War, presumably compiled by Roberts for a book or article. Roberts' files cover roughly the years 1849 through 1976, with a bulk focus on 1960 through 1975, and focus on, among other things, contacts between antiwar groups and communist governments, statements from the communist governments and insurgents of Vietnam, Laos, and Cambodia, and newspapers, magazines, and photographs about life on the Indochinese homefront. There is also a small amount of material related to activism on other subjects such as welfare reform.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Moss Roberts in 2007. The accession number associated with this gift is 2007.005.
Biographical Note
Moss Roberts (1937-) is a professor of East Asian Studies at New York University and has been teaching there since 1968. As a founding member of the Committee of Concerned Asian Scholars – a group which was founded in 1968 with the purpose of challenging what they saw as assumptions that led to the Vietnam War – Roberts has written articles for their journal, formerly the Bulletin of Concerned Asian Scholars from 1968 to 2000. Roberts has also researched and published in the areas of Chinese philosophy, literature, and language; Japanese literature; and modern Asian history. He has also published translations of Chinese texts.
Scope and Content Note
The Moss Roberts Vietnam War Research Files includes a variety of materials presenting the communist perspective of the Vietnam War created roughly between 1849 and 1979, with a bulk created between 1960 and 1975. These materials were compiled by Roberts, presumably during the course of research.
Materials are sorted into five series: four are based on themes that Roberts appears to have focused on in his research surrounding the Vietnam War, and one series contains documents related to research or work that was not related to the Vietnam War. Most of the types of materials are spread across the series and include correspondence, press statements, newspaper and magazine pages, newspaper and magazine articles, photographs, postcards, index cards, booklets, pamphlets, leaflets, underground journal articles, newsletters, and maps. Most materials are in English, although some are in French, Vietnamese, Khmer, and Lao.
The bulk of Series I is made up of press statements, communique, and documentation of news on the ground from communist forces in Vietnam, Laos, and Cambodia. Many of these are documentary packets compiled by the Democratic Republic of Viet Nam (DRVN) Committee on Cultural Relations which consists of reports on recent happenings in the war, excerpts from government media and Western media that sympathize with the Vietnamese plight, and war anecdotes. These statements all generally cover and valorize important communist military actions (i.e. the Battle of Khe Sanh and the Tet Offensive), decry Western hypocrisy in their proclaimed desires for peace, and speak about efforts to rebuild in the areas they occupy. Most statements are published in English, although there are some copies of documents in French and Vietnamese.
The correspondences in Series I are largely communications between leftist antiwar groups, such as the Indochina Solidarity Committee, the Indochina Peace Campaign, and the United States Committee to Aid the National Liberation Front of South Vietnam. Photographs in Series I depict topics from education and agriculture in the "liberated zones" of Indochina as well as leaders of the Provisional Revolutionary Government of South Vietnam as well as photographs of members of the Lao People's Liberation Army and the Lao Patriotic Front.
Series II includes correspondence between diasporic communities and communist governments. Topics discussed in these letters include public perception of the Vietnam War in America, the facilitation of informational materials between correspondents, political prisoners in South Vietnam, and federal attempts to deport Vietnamese-American antiwar protestors. This series also includes booklets, pamphlets, leaflets, flyers, and underground journal publications in the collection consist of antiwar materials created by organizations like the Indochina Solidarity Committee, the Indochina Peace Campaign, the Union of Vietnamese in Canada, and the Lao Student Union in France. Flyers and leaflets often advertise antiwar demonstrations, film screenings, or meetings or decry specific American military actions in Indochina. Booklets, pamphlets, and underground journals often cover topics like South Vietnamese political prisoners or American military strategy in Vietnam from a pro-Vietnamese, anti-capitalist perspective.
Series III mostly contains news and magazine clippings and papers culled from a variety of sources such as the North Vietnamese publication Vietnam to excerpts from Newsweek, Time, and the New York Times, to other lesser-known papers like the American Report. These are often excerpts from articles and sometimes include underlined sentences that were likely relevant to Roberts' research. Roberts also collected multiple newsletters from leftist and diasporic antiwar groups, underground journals, and bulletins published by antiwar groups and scholars. Series III contains also images documenting the damage caused by American bombing campaigns. All photographs are black and white. Some of these photographs include graphic pictures of injured and dead people.
Series IV consists of maps of Southeast Asia; folders of general information on Vietnam, Laos, and Cambodia containing newspaper and magazines clippings, booklets, pamphlets, press statements, and so on; and an economic report on Vietnam published during the 1970s by the United States Agency for International Development (USAID).
The collection also contains a small amount of material related to other leftist groups and activism including the International Socialist Club and Welfare Action Coalition. These materials are located in Series V.
Arrangement
These records have been arranged into five series based on topic. The content in each series has not been arranged. The series arrangement of the collection is as follows:
Series I. Indochinese Homefront
Series II. Western Antiwar Activity
Series III. Anti-Communist Authoritarianism and War Crimes
Series IV. General Sources on Southeast Asia
Series V. Other Activism
Vietnam -- Politics and government -- 1945-1975.; Research (document genres).; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements.; Roberts, Moss, 1937-
- Series I: Indochinese Home Front, 1960-1975
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of statements, document compilations, and communiques by the North Vietnamese governent, the Provisional Revolutionary Government of South Vietnam, National Liberation Front of South Vietnam, Pathet Lao, and the National United Front of Kampuchea; newspaper and magazine clippings and pages, photographs, and artwork of life in communist-occupied areas (referred to as "liberated zones"); and photographs of communist forces in Indochina.
  - "Political Programme of the South Vietnamese Front for Liberation", 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - National Liberation Front of South Viet Nam--Statements, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - National Liberation Front 10-point Program at Peace Talks, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - National Liberation Front--Documents, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Commemoration du VIe Anniversaire de la Fondation du Front National de Liberation du Sud Viet Nam, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Personalities of the South Vietnam Liberation Movement, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ho Chi Minh, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Viet Minh, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Northwest Fighting Against U.S. Aggression--film script translation, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Battlefront in the Sky--Draft, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Democratic Republic of Viet Nam (DRVN) Committee for Cultural Relations with Foreign Countries, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 2-5, Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Democratic Republic of Viet Nam (DRVN) Statements--General, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Leaders, People in the Democratic Republic of Viet Nam (DRVN), Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Children in the Democratic Republic of Viet Nam (DRVN), Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Defending the Democratic Republic of Viet Nam (DRVN), Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Democratic Republic of Viet Nam: Education, Medicine, Arts, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Democratic Republic of Viet Nam (DRVN): Statement at the Paris Peace Conference, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Provisional Revolutionary Government of the Republic of South Viet Nam--Leaders and People, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Provisional Revolutionary Government of the Republic of South Viet Nam, 1966-1975 (Box 3, Folder 9-10, Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Provisional Revolutionary Government of the Republic of South Viet Nam--Correspondence, 1970-1975 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Provisional Revolutionary Government of the Republic of South Viet Nam--Statements, 1968-1975 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Provisional Revolutionary Government of the Republic of South Viet Nam--Paris Peace Statements, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Full Text of Peace Agreements--Vietnamese Copy, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1973 Peace Agreement and Earlier Proposals, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 1973 Peace Agreement and Earlier Proposals--Press Clippings, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Vietnam News, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Indochinese Boards--Cultural, Undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Vientiane Controlled Zones, Undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Lao Display--Photographs, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Lao People's Liberation Army--Photographs, Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Lao Patriotic Front (LPF) Leaders and People--Images, Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Overseas Contacts with Cambodian Groups, 1973-1975 (Box 5, Folder 10, Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Royal Government of the National Union of Kampuchea (GRUNK) Question: U.N. General Assembly, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Liberated Zone--Images, 1972-1974 (Box 6, Folder 3-8)
  - Reconstruction in Liberated Zones, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Women in Vietnam, 1972-1974 (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
  - Graphics, 1972-1975 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Vietnamese Line Drawings, Undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - South Vietnam: Land and People--Drawings, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - South Vietnam Urban Uprising, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - People's Liberation Armed Forces--Photographs, Undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Vietnam People's Army Bulletin, January-February 1966 (Box Shared Tamiment 068, Folder 15)
- Series II: Western Anti-War Activity, 1965-1976
  This series consists of correspondences between the Indochina Solidarity Committee and leftist antiwar groups, Vietnamese, Laotian, and Cambodian diasporic antiwar groups, and communist governments; newsletters, bulletins, and drafts of publications from antiwar groups; flyers advertising antiwar events, and a collection of index cards of various pro-communist contacts, including North Vietnamese embassies and diasporic antiwar groups.
  - Indochina Peace Campaign, 1972-1974 (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
  - Indochina Resource Center, 1972-1975 (Box 7, Folder 7, Box 8, Folder 1, Box Shared Tamiment 068, Folder 17)
  - Indocina Solidarity Committee, 1972-1976 (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
  - Mailing lists, Undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Protest fliers, Undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Newsletter Artwork, January 1965 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Glad Day Press, 1970-1972 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Union of Vietnamese in the United States, 1973-1976 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Union of Vietnamese in Canada, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Union of Patriotic Vietnamese in Canada, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Association of Vietnamese Patriots in Canada, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Union of Vietnamese in France, 1972-1974 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Group of Khmer Residents in the United States, 1973-1976 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Lao Student Union in France, 1972-1974 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Lao Representation or Contacts, 1972-1975 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Series III: Anti-Communist Authoritarianism and War Crimes, 1962-1976
  This series consists of photographs documenting American and South Vietnamese war crimes (bombing dikes, killing civilians, etc.) and Vietnamese resistance (urban uprisings, political prisoners, etc.); articles and statements from governments pointing to evidence of violations of the Paris Peace Agreement; information on and statements from the Asia Foundation; and a folder of photographs clipped from mainstream American magazines and newspapers of the fall of Saigon. Many of the photographs in this series show graphic depictions of injured and dead people.
  - The Asia Foundation, 1962-1968 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - United States Genocide, Ecocide, Biocide in Indochina, 1967-1972 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - United States War of Aggression--War Crimes, Bombings, Undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - People Maimed, Injured, or Killed by United States Bombings, Undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - "Civilian War Casualties and Medical Care in South Vietnam", 1971 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Bombing, 1964-1968 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Automated Air War: Electric Battlefield, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - U.S. Destruction in the Democratic Republic of Viet Nam, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Documented U.S.-Saigon Violations of the Paris Peace Agreement, 1970-1974 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Dikes in Northern Vietnam, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - United States Bombing, Advisors, War Crimes, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Third Force--General, 1973-1974 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Political Prisioners, 1971-1973 (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
  - Pictures from the End of the War--Magazines, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Series IV: General Sources on Southeast Asia, 1849-1974; 1958-1974
  This series consists of maps of various parts of the world but especially Southeast Asia; folders of general information on Vietnam, Laos, and Cambodia containing newspaper and magazines clippings, booklets, pamphlets, press statements, and so on; and an economic report on Vietnam published during the 1970s by the United States Agency for International Development (USAID).
  - Maps, Undated (Box 10, Folder 8-14)
  - Articles on Vietnam--General, Undated (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Vietnam Economic Data (U.S.A.I.D), 1972-1974 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Vietnamese Documents, Statements, Reports, and Publications--General, Undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Articles on Cambodia, 1970-1974 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
  - Cambodia--General Information (Box 11, Folder 5, Box Shared Tamiment 068, Folder 16)
  - Letter from President Zachary Taylor to the King of Annam, 1849-1850 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Series V: Other Activism, 1971-1979
  This series contains materials that are not directly related to the Vietnam War. It consists of fliers, petitions, correspondence, newsclippings and images related to the International Socialist Club and the Welfare Action Coalition.
  - International Socialist Club, 1971-1975 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Welfare Action Coalition, 1977-1979 (Box 11, Folder 8-9)